This video is sponsored by DeleteMe.
Saudi Arabia's NEOM is an incredible
mega project set to propel the country
from the dark Middle Ages straight to
the high-tech Middle Ages. NEOM itself
is a collection of different mega
projects, each more impressive than the
rest. A global hub of innovation and
sustainable growth dreamt up by Mohammed
bin Salman, the world's most dedicated
tropical player and reigning Fruit Ninja
champion.
NEOM is set to be completed by 2030,
just 4 years. This begs the question,
where are they now? We will take a look.
And in the spirit of being constructive,
at the end I will also give some
practical advice to Saudi Arabia as to
how to actually handle this project. I
know you're watching this, Mohammed bin
Salman. What else would the Saudi ruler
do in his free time other than watching
Adam Something videos? Yeah, at this
point I cannot visit Saudi Arabia
because I'm pretty sure they would just
put me to death. So, NEOM has four key
parts: Trojena, Sindalah, the Oxagon,
and the Line. So, how are they coming
along? Where are they now in 2026, 4
years before the deadline? Let's look at
Trojena first, a luxury mountain
destination by NEOM, set to redefine
luxury mountain living and hospitality
while becoming a world-class center for
winter sports and adventure. Wow, thanks
ChatGPT. Now give me some ideas for what
to do with Khashoggi's pieces. Trojena
includes a giant Roomba on a mountain,
an alien mirror cave wall, a ski village
built on top of skyscrapers. Oh Jesus,
what is this? Is Saudi Arabia okay? Was
the CGI artist having a stroke? Wait,
are these skiing slopes built out of
rebar concrete? Oh yeah, dude, this is
how skiing works, definitely. It's a
shame Saudi Arabia is forced to build
these giant rebar concrete troughs for
people to ski in. Things would be so
much easier if only we had access to
these kind of big, naturally occurring
piles of rocks, you know what I mean? So
that when snow falls on them, we can
slide down on their sides or something.
Actually, hold on. I don't think we
realize the significance of what we're
looking at here. Guys, NEOM consultants
have invented mountains. Saudi Arabia
didn't just transition to the 21st
century, they went straight for 4.5
billion BC. What will they invent next?
Lakes? Oh, wait, they actually did. No,
guys, you don't understand. It's very
important to have this giant jutting
rebar concrete tub here hanging off the
cliff, which visitors won't even get to
see because it will be under them. Look
at these other mountain lakes. They're
so boring. I bet nobody even goes there.
Without a giant concrete bathtub built
into the mountain, who even cares,
right? Trojena though, so yeah, this is
not happening. Trojena has been
downsized and put on the back burner due
to cost overruns and doubts about its
feasibility. Imagine that. Speaking of
downsizing, how about we all downsize
the amount of personal data we have
scattered on the internet? And you can
easily do that with today's sponsor,
DeleteMe. It's a jungle out there. Some
people and even companies like certain
private companies colluding with the US
government whose name comes from Lord of
the Rings make a living by scraping your
personal data from wherever they can.
This data is then used to fine-tune
algorithms and to help the state surveil
you, for example. But having a bunch of
personal data online also leaves you
vulnerable to identity theft and
harassment. The safest choice is to keep
your digital footprint under your
control by removing superfluous personal
data from the internet. And you can do
that with DeleteMe. DeleteMe helps
remove your personal data by scanning
hundreds of data broker websites that
collect online personal data, yours
included. Experts at DeleteMe will then
request the removal of your data, thus
helping you reduce your digital
footprint. After a week, you get a
privacy report detailing what sort of
data was found and removed. DeleteMe
will rescan those websites later to make
sure that your data doesn't surface
anywhere else. Do not let your personal
data fall into the wrong hands. Get 20%
off DeleteMe consumer plans by going to
joindeleteme.com/adam20
and use the promo code adam20 during
checkout. That's
joindeleteme.com/adam20.
Promo code adam20. Thank you for
checking out DeleteMe. So, okay, NEOM.
Ideas that are very big and very stupid.
Because the dictator thinks that just
because he played Cities: Skylines for 2
hours, he is now the equivalent of a
civil engineer and architect at the same
time. Honestly, stuff like this reminds
me of Ceaușescu, the former Romanian
dictator that I talked about in my Dubai
video. He wanted a metro system for
Bucharest, the capital. So, engineers
were like, "Okay, so here's a sensible
plan for the metro system." But then
Ceaușescu was like,
"No. It has to go under the river,
parallel to it, in fact." But "But what
about the water? There There is a huge
risk of water breaking." "Would you like
to go to the gulag?" "Under the river it
is, sir." And then his wife, Elena
Ceaușescu, was like, "Um actually, the
students have gotten too fat, so uh
cancel this central metro station, Piața
Romană, so they will walk more." I am
not making this up, by the way. The
station itself that was, quote unquote,
canceled by Elena is still there today,
but it's super narrow because it was
built in secret. Because the engineers
realized how freaking stupid this was
and knew that a station was needed
there. So, they did it in a way that
Elena wouldn't notice. Prime banana
republic stuff. And of course, we all
laugh at this, right? Uh you know, some
uneducated tinpot dictator doing all
this funny  crazy stuff in their
backward, far away, primitive
dictatorship. But then we see stuff like
NEOM and half the people start clapping
like seals. Speaking of, the Oxagon, a
reimagined industrial city floating on
the water. It needs to do so because if
there is one thing Saudi Arabia lacks,
it's free space, right? Yeah, please
ignore that 2 million square kilometer
emptiness over there. Thank you. We got
to build on the water, guys. It's
cramped like the Netherlands over here.
Strategically located on the Red Sea
coast near global shipping lanes, Oxagon
is the ideal base for factories of the
future. But but you can just build this
on the coast. There's the coast. There
is land already. Just just put it next
to the water. You don't need to put half
of it on the water. What if there are
big waves, a storm? What if the Ever
Given Two crashes into it or something?
Yeah, it's like imagine some secret
Iranian covert ops mission where they
drive a full tanker into it and set it
on fire.
But inside the Oxagon, there will be all
these crazy science fiction factories
fusing principles of industry 4.0 with
the circular economy. Robotic arms,
windmills, plants, the T-virus from
Resident Evil, giant dice, glowing CPUs,
cyborgs, Mountain Dew, riffs through
space-time.
Now, you might say all of this is nice,
but oddly vague. What companies will
manufacture there? What will they
manufacture? How and why? I don't know.
You don't know. But that's okay because
nobody in NEOM knows either. What we're
looking at is shiny CGI slop produced by
consultants neatly fitted within the
attention span of relevant
decision-makers to bamboozle them into
approving this. And of course, the
Oxagon has a seaside future residential
thing with freaking flying cars because
why not? Also, look at how half the
women here are still wearing hijabs.
It's the future, but women showing their
hair in public would still cause males
to enter an uncontrolled sexual
psychosis, apparently. One moment you're
busy gene splicing cyber lettuce with
your holo watch, but then you see a
woman's exposed neck and hair or
something, so you just lunge at her like
a horny gorilla. Seriously though, the
same people pushing this techno future
mania in Saudi Arabia likely think that
Star Trek is degenerate for showing
women's bare legs. They like the
aesthetic of the future enough to draw
in venture capital money, but none of
that post Middle Ages enlightenment
degeneracy, please, like women's rights.
So, anyway, the Oxagon is basically a
seaport with some factories and a
residential area attached. Why does this
need to be a half-floating octagon at
sea? Because the shinier the project is,
the more likely it is to get approved.
That's why. Oh, and this is also not
happening due to it being an obviously
stupid and untenable idea. What they are
doing instead is building a seaport and
some apartments. Oh, and uh there will
be some kind of natural gas facility,
but that's okay. Rebranding this project
is easy. Just add an E to its name. And
now, let's look at the most notorious
symbol of Neom, The Line, the
170-km-long
desert skyscraper megacity. Seriously,
this thing is ludicrous. It's two
500-m-tall
skyscrapers running parallel next to
each other for 170 km in the desert,
completely straight. Why is it mirrored?
Because it looks cooler on renders. Once
again, consultants had to sell this to
MBS, and they had 60 seconds to do so.
Now, I have already made a video about
The Line, link below, where I covered
extensively why this is a deeply stupid
idea. I've also proposed some
alternatives, pictured here, which would
actually work much better, because The
Line, in its original form, is just a
perfect storm of bad ideas and general
stupidity. It takes all the
disadvantages of pre-planned cities and
skyscrapers and mashes them into
literally the worst, most inefficient,
and contrived thing to ever exist. For
example, since you're pressing
everything into 500-m-tall segments, and
you want to include every single amenity
in them, you will also have to build
hundreds of escalators and elevators per
segment. Let's say 500 elevators and
1,000 escalators. This includes
everything from main heavy-duty
elevators to the escalators between two
floors of H&M. Let's assume that one
segment is 2 km long. So, The line would
have 85 segments, well, would have had,
which nets us 42,500
elevators and 85,000 escalators. And
escalators need to be two-way, so we can
safely double that to 170,000.
If this thing gets built, it won't get
built, but still, find out which company
gets the order for escalators and
elevators, and then put your life
savings into their stocks. So, how is
this project going? When will the line
be completed? Well,
The line, massive progress revealed,
2025 update. Oh boy, I can't wait to see
what's happening over there. Oh wait,
it's just an AI slop voiceover video
with NEOM stock footage or it and the
video actually contradicts its own title
and thumbnail saying, correctly, that
it's not happening. Rather than the
traditional urban sprawl, this concept
would utilize state-of-the-art
technology and design initiatives to
stack everything vertically. God, I love
that AI voiceover reading out a script
presumably written by ChatGPT. The Saudi
government would be redirecting its
attention toward core economic sectors.
PIF wanted a more balanced portfolio,
and The Line represented a huge chunk of
red ink.
>> Contact us. Yeah, us, sure. What, are
there two of you? One of you presses the
generate button and the other handles
control C, control V. So, yeah, The Line
has been remodeled somewhat. Its brand
new iteration, The Dot, will welcome its
first residents sometime between 2040
and 2100.
So, the Saudi leadership, in particular
Mohammed bin Salman, looked at this
disaster, this increasingly costly war
on elementary school physics, which
Saudi Arabia is losing badly. So, they
thought, how could we propel ourselves
into the future without building
anything meaningful, impressive, or
complicated? Hmm. Oh, yep, yep, that's
right. AI data centers. Perfect,
just perfect. Do I even need to make a
joke here? No, I don't think so. This is
just too perfect. Some oil monarchy
dictatorship dreams up some BS mega
projects and they didn't work. So, yeah,
AI it is, guys. So, could this still be
fixed somehow? Could we still resurrect
NEOM, if you will? Well, yeah, actually,
it's completely possible. The proof of
that is Sindalah, the part of NEOM I
haven't yet talked about, which is
basically an island with a luxury hotel,
a marina, and of course a golf course,
of course. And this works because we
know how to build hotels, we know how to
build marinas, we know how to build golf
courses, and we know how to build it on
an island. Thanks, Dubai. And look, next
to it where the Oxagon would have been,
you already have some kind of seaport
going up. That's nice. So, okay, do
that. Build the seaport, good idea. We
know how to build seaports, you'll make
it happen. And the Oxagon could be
something like, I don't know, Black Mesa
from Half-Life? Desert, mountains, R&D
research complex, industrial production.
Because, yeah, it sounds funny, but with
the Oxagon, they basically want Black
Mesa. And this could kind of sort of
even work. Okay, not things like the
Lambda complex with the teleportation
labs, but you know what I mean. Hey,
companies, we have all these high-end
R&D spaces with generous state support
and tax benefits right next to a
seaport, and also with a high-speed rail
connection to the nearest airport. Bring
some of your departments and employees
here. There is a whole luxurious city
for them here with year-round free
access to our beach resorts. Oh, and
also like a 1% tax rate or something.
So, you know, it's kind of like the Star
Trek Enterprise. Come and work here for
some time, bring your family with you.
All amenities are included. I think it
could work like this, technically,
right? As for Trojena, I mean, look,
let's just build some mountain hotels,
some hiking trails, some skiing trails.
No need for these CGI artist stroke
victim skiing trowel reinventing
mountains type deal, okay? Just create
some nice-looking mountain resorts. And
as for The Line, that just has to go.
I'm sorry. Or hey, just do what I
recommended in my original line video,
The Tub. It's like The line, but it goes
in a circle. Oh, and this can actually
be built without bankrupting the
country. So, this is what I would do if
I was in charge of Saudi Arabia and I
really, really, really, really, really
wanted to build NEOM. Of course, if you
actually want to modernize your country,
you have to start with your existing
cities and of course, your society. I
would create Jeddah dumpster town. And
how nice would that be? So, this was
Saudi Arabia's NEOM in the year 2026.
Thank you for watching and if you like
my content, please consider becoming a
patron or a member here on YouTube. And
I'll be seeing you next time.